Guide to the Abbey Theatre records, 1910-1938
The New York Public Library. Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature.
Abbey Theatre records
1910-1938
Berg Coll MSS Abbey Theatre
19204
Card catalog available.
Abbey Theatre
The New York Public Library. Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
72 items
This is a synthetic collection consisting of manuscripts, typescripts, correspondence, financial and legal documents, and a portrait.
The Abbey Theatre in Dublin is an Irish theatrical company, founded in 1904 by William Butler Yeats and Lady Isabella Augusta Persse Gregory. J. M. Synge and Lady Gregory were its first directors. It is devoted to Irish drama.
Some of the materials were among Ria Mooney's correspondence and with Lady Gregory's correspondence.
This is a synthetic collection consisting of manuscripts, typescripts, correspondence, financial and legal documents, and a portrait. The manuscripts and typescripts include stage directions, lists of actors, extracts of reviews of performances, schedules, and other matters related to the Theatre, as well as articles, notes, and reviews by Sean O'Casey, a lecture by Alfred Wareing, and addresses by W. B. Yeats, Lady Gregory, and J. M. Synge. The correspondence, dating from 1910 to 1928, includes letters from the Theatre to Sean O'Casey, Lady Gregory, and W. B. Yeats, as well as letters relating to the Theatre between various correspondents, including Sara Allgood, Annie Elizabeth Fredericka Horniman, and Bertha June Lucas. The bulk of the collection consists of financial documents, specifically weekly returns dating from 1920 to 1931, financial statements, and lists of checks made out to various payees.
This is a synthetic collection, created from materials acquired through gift and purchase from various sources.
Abbey Theatre; Allgood, Sara, 1883-1950; Gregory, Lady, 1852-1932; Horniman, Annie Elizabeth Fredericka, 1860-1937; Lucas, Bertha June (Richardson), Mrs; Mooney, Ria, 1903-1973; O'Casey, Sean, 1880-1964; Synge, J. M. (John Millington), 1871-1909; Wareing, Alfred, 1876-1942; Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939; Correspondence
- Correspondence, 517907
  - Outgoing, 517908
    - Telegram to Lady Gregory, 1916 May 19; 517909; corr. out; 1 item (Manuscript box (Gregory))
    - 3 TN to Sean O'Casey, 1928 June 9 - 1928 June 30; 517910; corr. out; 3 items (Enclosed in: Sean O'Casey. Windfalls. Early typescript. On versos of p. 1-3 of rough draft of "The job." Envelope 1)
      Signed J. H. Perrin
    - Telegram to William Butler Yeats, 1913 Sept. 19; 517911; corr. out; 1 item (Manuscript box (Yeats))
      Came with Lady Gregory's papers
  - Incoming, 517912
    - Sean O'Casey. AL (draft) to the Abbey Theatre (?), n.d.; 517913; corr. in; 1 p (In his: Holograph notebooks. Vol. 3, p. [73])
    - John D Sinclair. TLS to Abbey Theatre. To W. B. Yeats?, 1906 June 20; 517914; corr. in; 1 item (Manuscript box (Gregory))
  - Related correspondence, 517915
    - Fred J. Harris. 2 TLS to Sara Allgood. Relates to Abbey theatre engagement of Miss Allgood, 1922 June 24, 1922 July 13; 517916; corr. About; 2 items (Manuscript box (Allgood))
    - Annie Elizabeth Fredericka Horniman. ALS to [--?]. Relates to the Abbey theatre, 1910 Dec. 7; 517917; corr. About; 1 item (Manuscript box)
    - Bertha June (Richardson) Lucas. ALS to Sara Allgood. Mentions W. B. Yeats and various Abbey Theatre actors and playwrights, 517918; corr. About; 7 p (Manuscript box (Allgood))
- Financial & Legal Documents, 517919
  - Financial Documents, 517920
    - Financial statement for the year ending Aug. 31, 1912. Typescript, 517921; financial docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box (Gregory))
    - Return for week ending 23rd Nov. [1918?]. Typescript (carbon), 517922; financial docs.; 1 item (On verso of first inserted page of: Lady Gregory. [The jester] Holograph outline, undated)
    - Returns for weeks ending Aug. 15, and Oct. 16, 1920, 517923; financial docs.; 2 items (Manuscript box)
      On versos of p. [4] and [6] of: Lady Gregory. [Aristotle's bellows] Songs. Holograph lists.
    - Returns for Sept. 9, 1920, 517924; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady I. A. P. Gregory. [Hugh Lane's life and achievement. London, 1921] Page proof. Following p. 172)
    - Returns for week ending April 16, 1921. Typescript, 517925; financial docs.; 1 item (Manuscript box (Gregory))
      On verso: Lady Gregory's holograph autobiographical notes Removed from: Lady Gregory. Memoirs. 14 holograph notebooks. Vol. 9
    - Returns for week ending Aug. 26, 1922. Typescript, 517926; financial docs.; 1 item (Manuscript box. In: Lady Gregory. [Memoirs] Typewritten draft. Folder 17)
    - Returns for week ending March 26, 1925. Typescript, 517927; financial docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box)
      On verso of: Lady Gregory. [On the racecourse] Holograph passage of dialogue, undated. 1 p.
    - Checks drawn, dated Jan. 28, 1926, made out to various payees. Typewritten list, 517928; financial docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box)
      On verso of: Lady I. A. P. Gregory. [Excerpts from her readings] Holograph, undated. 1 p. Mutilated
    - Returns for weeks ending May 1, 8, and 15, 1926, 517929; financial docs.; 3 items (Manuscript box. In: Lady Gregory. TL (copies) to John Quinn. Jan. 4, 1903-Feb. 6, 1924. On versos of p. 36, 30, 28 of carbon)
    - Return for week ending July 17, 1926. Typescript, 517930; financial docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box)
      On verso of p. 2 of typescript of: Lady Gregory. ALS to George William Russell, July 24, 1926
    - Returns for weeks ending Aug. 7 and 21, 1926. Typescript, 517931; financial docs.; 2 items (In: Lady Gregory. [Case for the return of Sir Hugh Lane's pictures to Dublin] Earlier typewritten draft)
    - Returns for week ending Sept. 11, 1926. Typescript, 517932; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 31. Carbon. On verso of p. 20)
    - Returns for week ending Sept. 18, 1926. Typescript, 517933; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 31. Carbon. On verso of p. 16)
    - Returns for week ending Oct. 2, 1926. Typescript, 517934; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 31. Carbon. On verso of p. 8)
    - Returns for week ending Oct. 9, 1926. Typescript, 517935; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 31. Carbon. On verso of p. 10)
    - Returns for week ending Oct. 16, 1926. Typescript (carbon), 517936; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 31. Carbon. On verso of p. 6)
    - Returns for week ending Oct. 23, 1926. Typescript, 517937; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 31. Carbon. On verso of p. 36)
    - Returns for week ending Oct. 30, 1926. Typescript, 517938; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 31. Carbon. On verso of p. 35)
    - Returns for week ending Nov. 6, 1926. Typescript, 517939; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 31. Carbon. On verso of p. 32)
    - Returns for week ending Dec. 4, 1926. Typescript (carbon), 517940; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 32. Carbon. On verso of p. 9)
    - Returns for week ending Dec. 18, 1926. Typescript, 517941; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 32. Carbon. On verso of p. 40)
    - Returns for week ending April 2, 1927. Typescript, 1927 Apr. 4; 517942; financial docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box)
      On verso of: Lady Gregory. AL (draft) to [--?], April 25 [1927] Removed from her: Journal, v. 35, p. 4238
    - Returns for week ending Aug. 13, 1927. Typescript, 517943; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. Figures in clay. Typewritten draft. On verso of p. [27])
    - Returns for week ending Feb. 11, 1928. Typescript, 517944; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 33. Carbon. On verso of p. 32)
    - Returns for week ending Feb. 25, 1928. Typescript, 517945; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 33. Carbon. On verso of p. 15)
    - Returns for week ending March 10, 1928. Typescript, 517946; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 33. Carbon. On verso of p. 41)
    - Returns for week ending March 24, 1928. Typescript, 517947; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 34. Carbon. On verso of p. 35)
    - Returns for week ending April 14, 1928. Typescript, 517948; financial docs.; 1 p (In: Lady Gregory. [Journal] Typescript. Book 35. Carbon. On verso of p. 7)
    - Returns for week ending Aug. 9, 1930. Typescript, 517949; financial docs.; 1 item (In: Lady Gregory. The volunteer bridge. Typescript. On verso of p. 2)
    - Lady Gregory. [Abbey theatre. Statement of returns for performances covering July 2, 1930-July 6, 1931] Holograph, 517950; financial docs.; 3 p (Manuscript box)
    - Returns for unspecified performances. Mutilated, n.d.; 517951; financial docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box (Gregory))
      Signed A. Patrick Wilson Came with Lady Gregory's papers
    - [Provision for disposal of trust funds] in event of winding up of company. Typescript with ms. corrections in an unidentified hand, 517952; financial docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box (Gregory))
    - List of expenses for production of Lady Gregory's Workhouse ward in an unidentified hand. Manuscript, 517953; financial docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box (Gregory))
    - Cheques, undated, made out to various payees. Typewritten list, 517954; financial docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box (Gregory))
      With Lady Gregory's marginal ms. note, "I am asking about this"
  - Legal Documents, 517955
    - Charles Prestwich Scott. [Abbey theatre. Typescript of arbitration between A. E. F. Horniman and the directors of the National Theatre Society, relating to the sale of the Abbey theatre, April 29, 1911]. Directors cited are Lady Gregory and W. B. Yeats, 517956; legal docs.; 1 item (Manuscript box (Gregory))
    - Agreement between Padraic Colum and the Directors of the Abbey theatre for permission to perform his play Thomas Muskerry, 1911 Aug. 17; 517957; legal docs.; 1 p (Manuscript box (Colum))
      Signed by W. B. Yeats and Padraic Colum
- Manuscripts & Typescripts, 517958
  - Manuscripts, 517959
    - The Abbey stage. Holograph measurements in an unidentified hand, 517960; ms.; 1 p (Manuscript box)
      Accompanied by photograph of exterior of Abbey theatre the morning of the fire (1951) Came with Ria Mooney's correspondence
    - List of players and payments essential in the event of a definite offer from Australia, in an unidentified hand. On letterhead of The Little Theatre, The Irish Players [London], 517961; ms.; 2 p (Manuscript box (Gregory))
    - Sean O'Casey. [Notes. Abbey Theatre] Plays ... 1929. Holograph. Schedule of Abbey Theatre performances, Jan. - Aug., 1929, 517962; ms.; 1 p (In his: Holograph notebooks. Vol. 7, unnumbered page at back)
    - Sean O'Casey. [Reviews. Peter Kavanagh; The story of the Abbey theatre. Notes] and holograph draft, 517963; ms.; 5 p (In his: Holograph notebooks. Vol. 19, p. [84-88])
    - Salary list proposed. Play proposed. Manuscript, n.d.; 517964; ms.; 2 p (Manuscript box)
      With: Lady Gregory. [Abbey theatre] Salaries. Loss, February to June. Holographs, undated. 5 p.
    - Alfred Wareing. The Abbey Theatre's first invasion of Britain. Holograph draft of lecture, 1938 Oct. 26 - 1938 Oct. 28; 517965; ms.; 14 p (Manuscript box (Gregory))
      Signed Enclosed in: Alfred Wareing. ALS and 6 TLS to Ethel Allenby. Letter of Oct. 25, 1938
  - Typescripts, 517966
    - English reviews (extracts) of Abbey theatre performances in England. Typescript, 517967; typescripts; 3 p (Manuscript box (Gregory))
    - Sean O'Casey. [Articles. Ireland] Seven typescripts with the author's ms. Corrections, 517968; typescripts (emended); 7 items (Cased)
      With: O'Casey v. Abbey. Typescript (photocopy). 39 p. Begun as letter to Ronald Ayling. On verso of p. 12 of "Abbey theatre": Macmillan & co., ltd., London. TLS to Sean O'Casey. July 12, 1934. 1 p.
    - Rules and regulations. Typescript (carbon) with Lady Gregory's ms. note, 517969; typescripts; 3 p (Manuscript box (Gregory))
      With envelope with Lady Gregory's ms. note: "Abbey fragment from Henderson's desk, given me 1929."
    - [Schedule of performances, June 12-17, 1922] Typescript, n.d.; 517970; typescripts; 1 p (Manuscript box. In: W.B. Yeats. TL (copies) to Lady Gregory. 1897-1910. 19 p. On verso of p. 6)
    - Statement for year ending 28th February 1914. Typescript, 517971; typescripts; 1 p (Manuscript box)
      With: Lady Gregory and W. B. Yeats. TLS (copy) to the editor of the Irish times. Abbey theatre, Dublin, Sept. 1914
    - W. B. Yeats, Lady Gregory, and J. M. Synge (?) [Abbey theatre. Address] Typescript with Lady Gregory's (?) ms. corrections. Address delivered to Abbey company over division of Abbey funds at Sept. 23, 1905, meeting, 517972; typescripts (emended); 2 p (Manuscript box)
- Portraits, 517973
  - Sara Allgood. Album of photographs. Contains 63 pieces, including Abbey theatre players, Lady Gregory, Lennox Robinson and Sir Roger Casement, 517974; portraits; 1 v (Cased)